Guide to the Rice University scrapbook collection, 1907-1985 UA 230
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series I: Rice Alumni Scrapbooks, 1912 - 1970; 130555
  - Alumni Association, 1958; 130848 (Box 30, Item 1)
    Football Coach Jess Neely is featured repeatedly; Prof. Radoslav Tsanoff on the occasion of his last public lecture before retiring; Dorothy McGee (24) appointed assistant to the registrar, the first woman to hold this type of job at Rice; Paula Meredith (25) appointed advisor to women, taking over the position from Mrs. Arthur Kotch; Prof. Marcel J. Moraud, head of the Department of Romance Languages on the occasion of giving his last public lecture before retiring in 1956 after 31 years at Rice; the Ryba twins engaged to marry two Rice athletic stars; J. Newton Rayzor, member of the second graduating class of Rice and donor of the Rice chapel and Memorial Center; Mr. and Mrs. Jesse Jones giving $1 million to Rice for the building of the first women's dormitory; Bo Hagan ap- pointed assistant football coach; George R. Brown honored as Houston Engi- neer of the Year; A. M. Tomforde (class of '17; death)(past president of Rice Alumni Association; supporter of Rice athletics); Burton McMurtry (presi- dent of Rice Student Association and Rondelet king); Rep. Albert Thomas (class of '20; running for re-election); S. G. McCann (death; dean of admissions and founding president of the Association of Rice Alumni); Charles Ives for scores of his presented to Fondren Library; Walter P. Moore (class of '27, engineer for promi- nent Houston buildings); President William V. Houston featured as a "Titled Texan"; Assoc. Prof. of History Frank Vandiver on publication of Rebel Brass and Mighty Stonewall, awarded best book by a Texan; Harris Masterson, re- ceiving Rice degree in 1955 after two interruptions for military service; Arnold Toynbee, visiting professor of history Dec. 1, 1957 to Jan. 30, 1958; Mrs. A. D. (Sully) Alsobrook, assistant for academic publishing; Dr. E. O. Lovett (death Aug. 14,1957); President Houston, one of two scientists appointed to assist Senate subcommittee on the nation's lagging missile and satellite program (following Sputnik); King Hill drafted by the Chicago Cardinals; Niels Bohr to address Rice Associates Dec. 17, 1957; Frank Ryan signing pro contract with the L.A. Rams; Wendel C. Ley (class of '32), "Neighbor of Note"; Prof. George Williams on the publication of his book Some of My Best Friends Are Professors; Tony Martino (death Dec. 2, 1958).
    Events of note covered in this scrapbook include announcement of design com- missioning for biology and geology buildings and auditorium (Aug. 29, 1955); con- struction of biology and geology buildings to start Sept. 23, 1956; beginning of a series of nine television programs, replacing the Sunday afternoon public lectures (which had been offered each year since 1912), scheduled for 7 PM the final Sunday of nine months; bell tower prank fatal to two Rice students from Houston; naming of five colleges for Mary Gibbs Jones, Capt. James A. Baker, William M. Rice, Jr., Harry C. Hanszen, and Harry C. Wiess; groundbreaking for Rice Memorial Chapel Nov. 10, 1957; largest attendance in history of Rice stadium, 72,000 at Nov. 16, 1957 football game of Rice against Texas A & M (which Rice won 7 to 6); opening of M. D. Anderson Biology Building Jan. 30, 1958; dedication of Hamman Hall (between acts of the faculty presentation of the Gilbert and Sullivan production Princess Ida) May 9, 1958; Rice computer construction beginning Sept. 11, 1958; dedication of Rice Memorial Center Nov. 8, 1958; installation of nuclear reactor in basement of chemical engineering building Nov. 22, 1958; first edition of The Journal of Southern History.
    The following are the most noteworthy activities represented in this scrapbook: annual football game benefiting Holly Hall, Rice freshmen vs. Texas A & M fresh- men; annual homecoming banquet of the Rice Alumni Association, Nov. 4, 1955 (which honored Coach Jess Neely); the annual Rice Follies, "Tonight on T.V." (to run two nights in the Bellaire H. S. auditorium); meeting of the Rice Institute Associates with Dr. W. F. Libby of the Atomic Energy Commission as speaker; annual Archi-Arts Ball with the theme "Milliareum Aureum" (cos- tumes of honorees represented countries of the Roman Empire); 15th Bien- nial Rice University Exposition for the public, demonstrating accomplishments in science, engineering, and the liberal arts (Apr. 27, 1956); Rondelet- May Fete May 5-6, 1956; commencement June 1, 1956 with speaker Dr. J. H. Van Vleck of Harvard on "The Age of Paradox"; 1956 annual homecoming dinner, at which honorees were Rice Professors Emeriti Marcel Moraud and Radoslav Tsanoff and Mrs. Jesse H. Jones; 1957 Archi-Arts Ball with the theme Kubla Kahn (Mongol Chinese emperor who ruled in fantasy over the imaginary pleasure kingdom of Xanadu); 1957 Rice Day on April 27, on which alumni competed in a "dress as you were" contest, the first prize going to Miss Sarah Lane in 1918 Women's ROTC uniform; 1957 Rondolet (photograph of May Queens through the years); May 1, 1957 Rice Players presenting Shakespeare's Merchant of Venice on the lawn between Lovett and the Physics Building; commencement May 31, 1957 with speaker Dr. Julius Adams Stratton, chancellor of M.I.T.; Archi-Arts Ball Feb. 15, 1958 with the theme Incubus (Nightmare); Rondelet May 2-4 1958; May 4, 1958 Shakespeare's Macbeth presented by Rice Players on the lawn in front of Lovett Hall (no admission charge); Homecoming Nov. 7-8, 1958.
  - Alumni Association, 1962; 130849 (Box 31, Item 1)
  - Alumni Association, 1963; 130850 (Box 31, Item 2)
    The content is a collection of newsclippings about people, events, and activities associated with Rice from September 1963 through March 1967. The lists that follow detail what is covered in addition to men's athletic teams and games. The newsclippings record accomplishments of Rice faculty, departments, and alumni; lectures being given at Rice by outside speakers; and student activities.
    People who are featured include Larry McMurtry at the film opening of Hud, based on his novel Horseman, Pass By; Jess Neely, honored as "Mr. Sportsman" of 1963, and at his retirement in 1966; F. Curtis Michel, potential Astronaut and later named one of the first six Astronauts; President John F. Kennedy, his arrival in Houston and his death in Dallas; Congressman Albert Thomas, appreciation dinner, honored with establishment of Political Science chair in his name by the Brown Foundation - death; Radoslav Tsanoff, returning to Rice as distinguished professor of humanities; Monroe K. Spears, joining the Rice faculty; John W. Cox, giving Rice 25-year lease of Yankee Stadium; Roland Pomerat, Rice organist, playing homemade harpsichord; Sarah L. Lane and Miss H. Lel Red, taking around-the-world trip; Dr. Frank Vandiver, first master of Brown College; Dr. Harold A. Wilson, founder of Rice Physics Dept. – death; Frank Ryan to teach math at Rice; Dr. Kennard Reed, Jr., first Negro on Rice faculty; Raymond Johnson, first Negro studying at Rice; Bobby May, winning Southwest Conference 120 and 440 hurdles and NCAA 120 high hurdles cham- pion; Prof. Angelo Miele on two-week speaking tour in Russia; Prof. James Castaneda, traveling to East to recruit students for Rice; Mr. and Mrs. George R. Brown, receiving Alumni Gold Medal for distinguished service to Rice; Harold (Bo) Hagan, named Rice football coach; Dr. William Houston, work in retirement.
    Events of note covered in this scrapbook include (chronologically) announcement of plans to build geomagnetic observatory north of Houston; beginning of Rice's Jefferson Davis Association; David Riesman on campus over several days for critique of Rice; installation of custom-built language laboratory; announcement of NASA grant for Rice to send four rocket probes into space; new electronic carillon in Rayzor Memorial Chapel; announcement of new Ryon Civil Engineering Labora- tories; "Sammy I" space probe instrument package, to be launched Jan. 14, 1964; suit to admit Negroes to Rice to be heard in court Feb. 10, 1964; Feb. 21, 1964, jury that is given eight issues to decide future policy at Rice upholds the Rice board; $20,000 gift enables printing of Jefferson Davis papers; March 9, 1964, Judge William Holland rules in favor of Rice Trustees; announcement of ten-year multi-million dollar expansion drive Oct. 11, 1964; ouster of Hugh Rice Kelly as editor of the Thresher; publication of Janus, a literary and creative arts journal; opening of Brown College; development of artificial heart jointly by Dr. Michael DeBakey and Rice group led by Prof. William Akers, and successful use in 37-year-old patient; Rice Players stage Harold Pinter's Birthday Party; personality study symposium with Margaret Mead giving closing address; announcement by Rice space scientists of discovery of a new stellar-planetary system; testimonial dinner for Jess Neeely; establishment of Center for Research in Social Change and Economic Develop- ment; Rice Players stage Edward Albee's Tiny Alice; Ken Kesey puts on improvisa- tion The Acid Test at Brown College March 16, 1967.
    Activities covered in this scrapbook include the old athletic stadium being used as a fine arts workshop; homecoming Nov. 8 and 9, 1963; 35-day celebration of the 400th anniversary of Shakespeare's birth, lectures to take place in Fondren Library; Archi- Arts Ball with the theme "Daemonia" Sat., Mar. 7, 1964; Pallas-Athene Literary Society to present Guys and Dolls; 1964 commencement with Dr. Charles H. Townes, provost and professor of physics at M.I.T. as speaker; 1964 homecoming; 1966 homecoming, with the first graduates, the class of 1916, being honored.
  - Cal Dean Hill, Jr., 1948-1950 (Box 39)
  - Tempe Howze, 1945-1949; 167192 (Box 42, Item 1-2)
    General note
    Tempe Howze graduated from Rice Institute in 1949 with a bachelor's degree. She was Miss Engineer '48-'49, Junior Class Vice-President, and one of the most popular girls on campus. Her scrapbooks includes photographs of campus scenes, Naval ROTC, Rally Club members, picnics, beach trips, and Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society formals. Photographs and newsclippings also feature Leonard L. Attwell, Jr., also class of '49 whom Tempe dated and later married.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original scrapbook returned to owner. Digital version is available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/95190
  - Andrew B. Bryan, 1920-1923 (Box 43)
  - Alumni Mailings Scrapbook, 1980-1983 (Box 45, Item 1)
    This scrapbook came from the Rice University Association of Alumni Records UA 003.
  - Class of 1933 Golden Anniversary Scrapbook, 1983 (Box 45, Item 2)
  - Class of 1932 Golden Anniversary Scrapbook, 1982 (Box 46, Item 1)
  - Ed Jennings scrapbook, 1942-1948 (Box 47)
  - Joan Wilson Scrapbook, 1933 (Box 48)
    Donated by Hilary Bobker (daughter of Joan Wilson) via Melissa Kean in July of 2019.
    Related Materials
    Scrapbook relates to Joan Wilson's existing scrapbook in the MS 303 Harold Albert Wilson Papers.
- Series II: Other Scrapbooks, 1907 - 1985; 130556
  This series includes scrapbooks of Rice University departments, Rice-related events, and other materials related to the life of the university which do not belong in other record groups.
  - Treasurer's Office, 1907 - 1926; 130851 (Box 32, Item 1)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1907 - 1940; 130852 (Box 32, Item 2)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1940 - 1949; 130853 (Box 32, Item 3)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1941 - 1945; 131517 (Box 32, Item 4)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1945 - 1947; 131518 (Box 33, Item 1)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1947 - 1950; 131519 (Box 33, Item 2)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1950 - 1953; 131520 (Box 33, Item 3)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1954 - 1955; 131521 (Box 34, Item 1)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1955 - 1958; 131522 (Box 34, Item 2)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1958 - 1962; 131523 (Box 34, Item 3)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1962 - 1964; 131524 (Box 34, Item 4)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1964 - 1969; 131525 (Box 35, Item 1)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1969 - 1972; 131526 (Box 35, Item 2)
  - Treasurer's Office, 1972 - 1980; 131527 (Box 35, Item 3)
  - Oil Properties newsclippings, 1942 -1944; 131528 (Box 35, Item 4)
  - Graphic History of Production and Development, Continental-Rice-Davis Joint Leasehold, Starr County, Texas, 1958; 131529 (Box 35, Item 5)
  - Development Office, 1950 - 1959; 131530 (Box 36, Item 1)
  - Mechanical Engineering Building, 1985; 131531 (Box 37, Item 1)
  - Allen Center for Business Activities Open House, 1967; 131532 (Box 38, Item 1)
  - Sewall Hall Groundbreaking, 1969; 131533 (Box 38, Item 2)
  - Rice University Semi-Centennial, 1962; 131536 (Box 40, Item 1)
  - Archi-Arts Scrapbook, 1945-1951 and 1954, 163119 (Box 41)
    The scrapbook, donated by Dr. Anderson Todd of the Rice School of Architecture, contains program material and photographs that both represent each year's distinct theme and identify the women honorees, who were elaborately costumed in keeping with each year's theme.
    1945 The title was "Guaya-Guayere," a port city on the island of Trinidad. The honorees were costumed to represent eight port cities which a Trinidadian sailor might have visited: Port of Spain, Trinidad; Port au Prince, Haiti; New Orleans, U.S.A.; Paramaribo, Surinam; Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; Guantanamo, Cuba; Forte de France, Martinique; and Kingston, Jamaica. The event was held at the Junior League Club on May 5. There are 11 photographs.
    1946 The theme was "Schauspielmaske," and the honorees were costumed to represent emotions: Love, Jealousy, Temptation, Modesty, Serenity, Gaiety, Vice, and Vanity. The event was held at the State Guard Armory on January 19. There are 10 photographs of the costumed women.
    1947 The theme was " L'Abeidem," a festival celebrated annually in medieval France and climaxed by the presentation of princesses from whom the knight victorious in the jousting tournaments would make a choice. The event was held at the Elks Hall on February 21. There are one large photograph of seven "princesses" in costume and seven small ones of men students apparently beginning to decorate. Also included is a page from the university yearbook.
    1948 The theme was "Jabberwocky," a fantastic wonderland on the other side of an enchanted Looking Glass. Costumed "characters" included Alice, the White Rabbit, a Magician, and two Pages, in addition to "the Favorites": Sleeping Beauty, Cinderella, Princess on the Glass Hill, Snow Queen, Andine, Proserpine, Titania, Pandora, and Ching Linyi, Chinese Bellmaker's daughter. The event was held at the Elks Hall on February 21. There are 25 photographs. Also included is the full page newspaper feature on the ball that appeared in the Houston Post as well as two pages from the university yearbook.
    1949 The theme was "Sargasso," based on the idea that the Sargasso Sea is the place where all the rivers of the earth, after flowing into the oceans, have gathered. There were 10 costumed honorees, representing the Euphrates, the Mississippi, La Plata, the Danube, the Volga, the Nile, the Congo, the Amazon, the Thames, and the Ganges. The event was held at the Elks Hall on March 12. There are 10 fine 8x10 labeled photographs.
    1950 The theme was "Danse Macabre," based on a fantasy involving the poet Baudelaire and the domain of Satan. The honorees were costumed as personifications of Baudelaire poems: L'Harmonie du Soir, L'Ideal, Ciel Brouille, La Beaute, La Muse Venale, L'Obsession, La Musique, La Geante, Parfum Exotique, and Reve Parisien. The event took place on February 11. There are nine labeled 8x10 photographs of the personifications.
    1951 The title was "Tyn El-k'hani 1202." This event is represented by only an admission ticket; there is no program with explanatory detaILs. It took place at Temple Emanu El on February 17.
    1954 The title was "The Neon Hours," referring to the night-time world. The eight honorees represented Neon, Society, Theater, Burlesque, Crime, the Foreign Element, Love, and Sunrise. Location and date are not recorded. There is one large photograph of one of the costumed women.
  - World War II scrapbooks, circa 1939-1945 (Box 44)
    Five scrapbooks created during World War II. Many of the creators of the scrapbooks are not identified, but the topics include U.S. Occupation of Japan, parachute training, European reconnaissance photographs taken by Marjor W.T. Eldridge, III; and Munich after World War II.